<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The triall of a black-pudding. Or, The unlawfulness of eating blood proved by Scriptures, before the law, under the law, and after the law. By a well wisher to ancient truth.</title>
            <author>Barlow, Thomas, 1607-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B846</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E666_2</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">50805969</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 50805969</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166177</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78170)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166177)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 102:E666[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The triall of a black-pudding. Or, The unlawfulness of eating blood proved by Scriptures, before the law, under the law, and after the law. By a well wisher to ancient truth.</title>
                  <author>Barlow, Thomas, 1607-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by F:N. and are to be sold by John Hancock in Popes Head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A well wisher to ancient truth = Thomas Barlow. Cf. ESTC.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 3".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Blood --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166177:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRIALL OF A BLACK-PUDDING.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> The unlawfulneſs of Eating Blood proved by Scriptures, <hi>Before</hi> the LAW, <hi>Under</hi> the LAW, and <hi>After</hi> the LAW.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> A well wiſher to Ancient Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>F: N.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>John Hancock</hi> in Popes Head-Alley. 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:166177:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166177:2"/>
            <head>THE TRIALL OF THE BLACK PUDDING: <hi>OR,</hi> THE EATING OF BLOOD <hi>Queſtioned, Convinced, Condemned.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have at laſt got a Copie of the Treatiſe, you mentioned to me, but with much ado, and for a ſhort time. I made uſe of my ſpare houres to extract the ſumme of it, which here I do impart, and commend to your more ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I confeſſe, I was always tender in that point, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what or how to reſolve; ſeeing on one ſide expreſs and literal Scripture inhibitions; on the other ſide, the Churches practiſe and approbation; and being loath to lay an unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie burden upon my conſcience, and yet fearing to tranſgreſs ſo plain and literal inhibitions, my judgement was diſtracted between fear to be accounted ſingular, if I ſhould abſtain; and fear to tranſgreſs a Law, if I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. Now this Treatiſe in my opinion doth make the point clear enough to any rationable man, that will ſubmit rather to the word, and be ruled by it, then to the conceits and practiſe of men. I do wonder, you do ſo violently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt it, as Judaical, and Moſaical, when we ſee the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:166177:3"/>Apoſtles Canon and Decree, touching this and other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints, was publiſhed and enjoyned then, when all other parts of the Ceremonial Law were altogether aboliſhed, and this Law againſt Eating of Blood <hi>de novo</hi> re commanded, and recommended to all Chriſtians practiſe and obſervation, you will ſee mo e of it in this Extract, which if you like, I wil endeavour to get the whole Treatiſe, and impart it to you, Herein onely I differ from the Author, that he maketh this reſtraint from eating of Blood Generall and binding of all men, as men: Whereas, I rather think, it doth concern and oblige onely Gods people, and under the Goſpel all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and ſuch as make profeſſion of Jeſus Chriſt. For what have we to do with them, that are without? I pray, read it without pre-conceit, conſider it without partialitie, and judge it without paſſion. Farewell.</p>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE QUESTION IS,</hi> Whether it be lawfull to Chriſtians under the Goſpel, to eat Blood?</head>
               <p>THe Author anſwereth <hi>Negatively,</hi> and ſaith No, it is not lawfull: and doth prove it by one Generall, and three ſorts of particular grounds and Arguments.</p>
               <p>The main Argument is this:</p>
               <p>That precept, or command, which God hath given to man before the Law, renewed to the Iſraelites under the Law, confirmed to Chriſtians after the Law, without any diſtinction of Times, Places, Perſons, is Moral, and perpetuall. But the Law againſt eating of Blood was thus given, before, under, and after the Law, and never repealed. <hi>Ergo</hi> that Law is Moral and perpetual.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Major</hi> or <hi>Propoſition</hi> of this ſyllogiſme is thus proved; becauſe 1. the whole time of the Churches ſubſiſting on Earth is divided into theſe three ages, before, under, and after the Law; ſo that what Command of God ſoever was given in any one of theſe three ages, it did binde all and every one
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:166177:3"/>in the Church, during that age of the Church. Now the ſame Command againſt Blood, being re-confirmed in all three ages, it was made binding of all men in the Church in all theſe three ages, and conſequently for ever. 2. Becauſe we can hardly finde any ſuch command of that Nature, but was either natural or moral; as the Law of keeping the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and againſt murther, which being made in all three Ages, doth prove it moral and perpetual.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> or <hi>Aſſumption</hi> is contained in the very words of Scripture. For this precept was given <hi>before</hi> the Law, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.4: renewed <hi>under</hi> the Law, <hi>Levit.</hi> 17.10. <hi>ſeq:</hi> confirmed <hi>after</hi> the Law, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.28. <hi>Ergo</hi> this precept is moral and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Circumciſion was commanded before, and under the Law, and practiſed after the Law, <hi>Ergo</hi> it doth not follow, that whatſoever hath a footing in theſe three Ages, is moral, &amp;c. <hi>R:</hi> 1. Though Circumciſion was commanded before, and under the Law, yet not after the Law, but rather expreſly forbidden. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.10, 19.24. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Ergo</hi> the compariſon faileth. 2. Circumciſion was commanded before the Law, but onely to one man, <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his poſteritie, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently doth and cannot binde all men, as the Law againſt Blood, which was given to <hi>Noah,</hi> and his poſteritie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to all men.</p>
               <p>The <hi>particular</hi> Arguments againſt Eating of Blood are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from ſeveral places of Scripture, in all the three Ages of the Church, which the Author doth proſecute largely, the ſum whereof is, as followeth.</p>
               <div n="1" type="answer">
                  <head>I. From the command of God <hi>before</hi> the Law, <hi>Gen</hi> 9.4.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But Fleſh with the life thereof, which is the Blood thereof, ye ſhall not eat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In theſe words of Gods inhibition, the Author findeth three grounds againſt Blood.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. From the <hi>Perſons,</hi> to whom this Command was given, <hi>Noah,</hi> his ſons, and poſteritie, <hi>v.</hi> 1.9. from whence he doth conclude:</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:166177:4"/>
                  <p> Whatſoever Command was given to Man as Man, at the beginning of a 2d. Creation, without any repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it in after ages, that Command is Morall and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall. But this Command was thus given. <hi>Ergò.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is undoubted. The <hi>Minor</hi> appeareth in the text; where we ſee, that the Law againſt eating of Blood was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the ſame perſons, to whom the bleſſing of multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was given, <hi>v:</hi> 1. the dominion over the Creatures. <hi>v:</hi> 2. the permiſſion to eat fleſh, <hi>v.</hi> 3. the command againſt ſhedding of Blood. Now all theſe particulars belong properly to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, without diſtinction of Perſons. <hi>Ergò</hi> the Law againſt Blood alſo, which conſequently is Morall and perpetuall.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. From Gods own <hi>reaſon,</hi> why he would have us abſtain from Blood; <hi>becauſe Blood is the life of the fleſh, i: e:</hi> bloud doth contain, and maintain, and convay the vitall ſpirits to all the parts of the body, which receive their ordinary nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Blood, ſo that blood being taken away, their lives are taken away. Now God would not have Men eat the life and the ſoul of Beaſts, a thing barbarous and unnaturall; ſo that if it was unlawfull then, it is unlawfull ſtill to eat Blood, becauſe Blood is ſtill the life of beaſts, from whence he concludeth:</p>
                  <p>Whereſoever the ſame reaſon, and ground of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand continueth, there the Command it ſelf continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in force, till it be expreſſely aboliſhed. Now the reaſon, why God would have Men abſtain from eating of Blood, continueth; becauſe it is the life of Beaſts. <hi>Ergò.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> The fourth Command hath a continuing reaſon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, becauſe the Lord reſted the Seventh Day, and yet that day is altered. <hi>Ergò</hi> a perpetuall reaſon doth not always proove the perpetuity of a command.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw:</hi> The change of the day of Sabbath is by an expreſſe order from God and his Apoſtles; but we have no ſuch change or alteration of the Law againſt eating of Blood, which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the <hi>Major,</hi> as a limitation, <hi>Ergò</hi> it continueth ſtill.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. From Gods <hi>End</hi> in this precept, which was, according
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166177:4"/>to the beſt Fathers and Divines opinion, to teach us humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, meekneſs, bowels of mercy: as if God had ſaid, I would have you abſtain from eating the blood of Beaſts, that ſo ye might be the more carefull to abſtain from ſhedding the blood of Men. Now this end of God continueth ſtill, who will have us ſtill to labour for humanity, kindneſs, tender-heartedneſs, <hi>&amp;c. Eph:</hi> 4.32: <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.22. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12. and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the means to attain this end muſt continue. From whence he gathereth this concluſion:</p>
                  <p>Where the end intended by God in a Command doth continue, there the means appointed by God for that end ought to continue, unleſſe they be expreſſely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden. Now the end intended by God in this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand doth ſtill continue. <hi>Ergò.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj:</hi> The end cannot proove the command laſting, unleſſe it can be prooved by the mind of the Lawgiver, that the Command is the onely perpetuall means to continue for that end: which cannot be ſaid of abſtaining from Blood, to be the onely, perpetual means to teach us humanity <hi>&amp;c. R:</hi> An abſurd conſequence: To abſtaine from Blood is not the onely means, to teach us humanity, <hi>Ergò</hi> we ought not abſtain from Blood. God preſcribeth many means to attain to one, and the ſame end, for the good of body and ſoul; as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, to eat, drink, reſt, exerciſe, and uſe Phiſick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for outward health: and to hear, read, pray, meditate, conferr, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for our ſpirituall health: All theſe particulars ſerve for the ſame end, yet we cannot ſay any one of them to be the onely means, and yet we are bound, as occaſion is offered, to make uſe of all, ſhall we not eat, nor ſleep <hi>&amp;c</hi> becauſe it is not the onely means to preſerve our health? ſhall we not hear, or pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe neither of it is the onely means to preſerve Grace in us? God forbid. If God appointeth a thing to be a means to obtain an end, whether it be the onely, or perpetuall means, or one of the means, we are bound to uſe it, as long as it may be a means to obtain that end, unleſſe it be expreſſely prohibited of God. Now God having appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the abſtaining from blood, as a means to teach us humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we muſt uſe it, till we are forbidden it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="answer">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:166177:5"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>II.</hi> From the Command of God <hi>under</hi> the Law, Levit. <hi>17.</hi> v: <hi>10.14.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And whatſoever man there be, of the houſe of Iſrael, or of the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, that ſo journeth amongſt you that eateth any manner of blood, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From theſe and the following words, the Author draweth three arguments more; as,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. From the <hi>repetition</hi> of the firſt naturall reaſon, which God gave to <hi>Noah,</hi> and his Sonns, becauſe blood is the life of Beaſts: to ſhew, that the ſame ground and reaſon continuing ſtill, for which God at firſt had forbidden the eating of Blood, the duty ſhould continue likewiſe; and that the Iſraelites as Men, and of <hi>Noahs</hi> Poſterity were bound to obſerve this Law, as long as this reaſon continueth; from whence he conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thus:</p>
                  <p>Whatſoever Law or precept was given to the Iſralites, as <hi>Noahs</hi> poſterity, that Law is Morall and Perpetuall. But this Law againſt eating Blood was thus given. <hi>Ergò</hi> it is Morall and Perpetuall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> The main reaſon added to the renewing of this Law was Ceremonall, and Typicall. <hi>v:</hi> 12. <hi>For I have given you the Blood upon the Altar,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ergo</hi> this Law bound no others but the Iſraelites; and no more, then other Ceremoniall Laws.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R:</hi> Though one reaſon alleadged in this Chapter was cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall, and bound onely the Iſraelites, yet there were other reaſons more generall and morall, which bound all men, as that <hi>naturall</hi> reaſon, <hi>v:</hi> 11. <hi>Becauſe the blood is the life of Beaſts,</hi> and a <hi>judiciall</hi> reaſon, that elſe God would puniſh them, and <hi>cut them off, v:</hi> 10.19. <hi>ſeq:</hi> And God gave here a threefold reaſon, <hi>naturall, myſticall,</hi> and <hi>judiciall</hi> reaſon, in the confirmation of this Law to the Iſraelites, to tie the Iſraelites the faſter to the obedience of this Law, as Men, Iſraelites, and in Covenant with God. <hi>A threefold cord is not eaſily broken, Eccleſ:</hi> 4.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. From the <hi>Perſons</hi> to whom this renewed command was given, viz: to all Men, <hi>Whatſoever Man there be.</hi> And leaſt they ſhould apply it to all Men onely that were Iſraelites, and in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166177:5"/>the Covenant, it is added, <hi>whether he be of the houſe of Iſrael, or of the ſtrangers, that ſojourn amongst you, v:</hi> 10. as if God would ſay, All men, and every one of you, none excepted, of what Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Religion, profeſſion ſoever, if he live or ſojourn amongſt you, ſhall be bound to this Law. From whence the Author argueth thus:</p>
                  <p>Whatſoever Law amongſt the Iſraelites, did not only bind themſelves, but their ſtrangers alſo that did but ſojourn amongſt them, that Law is Morall, and Perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall. But the Law againſt eating Blood, did bind all ſtrangers. <hi>Ergò.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is certain: becauſe no ſtranger or alien durſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ amongſt the Iſraelites, but was bound to obſerve all Morall Laws, though he was freed from all Ceremonial Laws. For the ſtrangers needed not to be circumciſed, or to eat the Paſſeover; but they were bound to keep the Sabbath, <hi>Exod:</hi> 20.13. <hi>Nebem:</hi> 13.16.20. and durſt not blaſpheme or curſe, <hi>Levit:</hi> 24.16. and the like.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is in the words of the Text. <hi>Ergo</hi> the concluſion is infallible.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> There were two ſorts of ſtrangers amongſt the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites; <hi>One</hi> by deſcent and birth, but not by Religion, being proſelites to the Jewiſh Religion, and theſe were bound to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all Ceremonies, and amongſt the reſt, to forbear from Blood: The <hi>other</hi> ſort of ſtrangers was both by birth and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, aliens from the Iſraelites, and not bound to Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Laws, neither to abſtain from blood, as it appeareth out of <hi>Deut:</hi> 14.21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R.</hi> 1. The diſtinction is true, but not ſufficient. For we find three ſorts of ſtrangers amongſt the Iſraelites, 1. <hi>proſelites,</hi> which were called ſtrangers within the Covenant, 2. <hi>Sojour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> called ſtrangers within the gates. 3. <hi>Aliens,</hi> which were open Idolaters, living in neighbour Countries about them. The <hi>firſt</hi> ſort of them was bound to all Laws, Morall, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall, Politicall: The <hi>ſecond</hi> ſort to Morall, and in ſome reſpect to Politicall, but to no Ceremoniall Law at all. For whoſoever would live or ſojourn amongſt them, muſt yeeld and ſubmit himſelf to the ſeven great commandments, which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166177:6"/>were given, according to the Hebrews relation, to the Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi> amongſt which one was to abſtain from Blood. The <hi>third</hi> ſort of ſtrangers durſt not live or ſojourn amongſt them at all, as <hi>Ainſworth</hi> and other learned men report. Now the Law againſt Blood was given not only to ſtrangers proſelites, but to ſtrangers ſojourners, which though not of the Jewiſh Religion, yet ſojourning amongſt them were bound to it, as appeareth by what is ſaid. <hi>Ergo</hi> by this expreſſion are not onely underſtood Proſelites, but even Heathen, and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, if within the gates. 2. The place of Scripture alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of <hi>Deut:</hi> 14, 21. where God gave leave to ſtrangers, <hi>to eat that, which dieth of it ſelf;</hi> and to the Jews, <hi>to ſell it them to eat,</hi> though they themſelves durſt not eat it: this can prove no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt the Morality and perpetuity of the Law againſt eating Blood. For 1. Suppoſe God had given the ſtrangers leave to eat Blood in the carkaſe, which yet is not: he might take it as a particular exception to the generall rule, for that time. Now <hi>Exceptio firmat regulam in non exceptis.</hi> 2. Though eating of Blood was a ſin in it ſelf, yet Gods extraordinary warrant and permiſſion intervening, doth make it lawfull to that Perſon, and for that time, that it was allowed. To mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or to robb is a great ſin; yet Gods Command to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to ſacrifice his Son, <hi>Gen:</hi> 22.2. or Gods permiſſion (at leaſt) if not command to the Iſraelites to robb the Aegyptians. <hi>Exod:</hi> 3.22. and 12.35.36. did not make murther or robbing lawfull, or aboliſh the Law againſt them. 3. It doth not follow, the Aliens might eat that, which died of it ſelf, <hi>Ergo</hi> they might eat Blood. For either they did eat the carkaſe cleanſed from Blood, as <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> upon the <hi>Acts</hi> 15. judgeth: or they did not eat that Blood, which was forbidden by God, <hi>viz:</hi> ſuch Blood, as might and ſhould be powred out, in which the ſoul or life of the Beaſt goeth out. For this Blood was properly forbidden by God, <hi>Levit:</hi> 17.12. There was a great difference between Blood and Blood amongſt the Jews. And ſome blood was abſolutely forbidden, other Blood lawfull to be eaten, even amongſt the moſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and moſt ſuperſtitious. The Hebrews ſay, that he only was guilty, which did eat the Blood of Beaſts and Fowls: but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166177:6"/>they might eat the Blood of Fiſhes and Locuſts, if clean, as <hi>Ainſworth</hi> reporteth upon <hi>Levit:</hi> 17.10. To apply this, the Blood that is left in a carkaſe cannot properly be ſaid to be the forbidden Blood, <hi>ergo</hi> the eating of it doth not aboliſh the Law againſt eating of Blood. In which reſpect the Latin cals a carkaſe <hi>ex ſangue cadaver.</hi> 4. The difference of puniſhment, which God threatneth to ſuch as eat Blood, or a dead car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſe, doth cleerly prove a great difference in the act or ſin it ſelf. For God will cut him off, and ſet his face againſt him, that eateth Blood, <hi>Levit.</hi> 17.10. but he that eateth of a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſe, ſhould only waſh his cloaths, bath himſelf in water, and be unclean untill the Even. <hi>v:</hi> 15. This ſhould be a ſufficient anſwer to the Objection.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Argument is drawn from the <hi>Threatning</hi> of Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment annexed to it: <hi>I will even ſet my face against that ſoul which eateth Blood, and will cut him off from amongst his people.</hi> Now we can hardly find ſuch an expreſſion, where the Lord threatneth any puniſhment to Men for breaking Ceremoniall Laws; It is true God will many times have the tranſgreſſors of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall Laws to be cut off by men, <hi>i: e.</hi> either by an <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall</hi> cenſure of excommunication; or a <hi>civill</hi> puniſhment by death to be afflicted, as we read <hi>Gen:</hi> 17.14. <hi>Exod:</hi> 12.19. <hi>Levit:</hi> 22.3. But we never, or hardly find, that God threatens ſuch an immediate kind of puniſhment by <hi>Himſelf,</hi> to Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall tranſgreſſions, as he doth here in this place, <hi>Lev:</hi> 17. where God threatneth to be not only the <hi>Judge,</hi> but the <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner</hi> alſo: as God doth oft in Morall tranſgreſſions; <hi>Levit:</hi> 20.3 6 <hi>Jerem:</hi> 44.11. <hi>Ezek:</hi> 14.8 &amp; in other places, from whence the Author thus concludeth:</p>
                  <p>Whereſoever God annexeth a threatning of immediate judgment from Himſelf to a Law, that Law is Morall and Perpetuall: Now in this Law God doth it. <hi>Ergo</hi> it is Moral and Perpetuall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj</hi> There are many ſuch expreſſions of Gods threatning puniſhment to ceremoniall tranſgreſſions, and amongſt the reſt, <hi>Levit:</hi> 23.29, 30. <hi>Ergo</hi> this is no ſufficient proof for the Moralitie of this Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R,</hi> 1. We do not ſee it yet, nay not in that place alleadged,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166177:7"/>
                     <hi>Lev:</hi> 23.29, 30. for in that Law of keeping the day of atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, two things are to be obſerved; the <hi>morall</hi> part of it, which is to keep ſuch a day, and to afflict our ſouls <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> part of it, to keep that day of atonement yeer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, upon the tenth day of the ſeventh moneth, which was a Ceremoniall Ordinance, binding only the Iſraelites; for we may keep ſuch dayes of atonement at any other convenient time. Now God threatneth a twofold judgment, the one to be inflicted by men, <hi>he ſhall be cut off from amongſt his people,</hi> for theſe outward or ceremoniall neglects or tranſgreſſions, which Man is able to diſcern and to diſcover: But the other judgment God reſerveth to himſelf, for the neglect of thoſe morall duties, which Man cannot diſcern, but only He that knoweth the hearts of men, as, <hi>for not afflicting their ſouls,</hi> and ſincerely humbling themſelves, but reſting in outward du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. We anſwer, that if God doth threaten ſuch immediate judgments to Ceremoniall tranſgreſſions, then it is in ſuch caſes only, where a Morall tranſgreſſion is joyned to Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, and cannot be ſevered one from another; but we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find any ſuch threatning denounced to meerly Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall breaches, and offences alone.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And this <hi>Calvin</hi> takes notice of in his <hi>Comment,</hi> upon <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit:</hi> 17.10. where he ſaith: <hi>God doth not only command to put to death thoſe, which ſhould defile themſelves in eating Blood, but he doth threaten to take vengeance. Himſelf, though they ſhould eſcape the band of the Judges. For the words do not only exhort the Judges, to do their Office, but that he doth reſerve a puniſhment to himſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="answer">
                  <head>III. From the Command of God <hi>after</hi> the Law. Act. 15.28, 29</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt, and to us, to lay upon you no greater burden, then theſe neceſſary things: that ye abſtain from meats offered to Idols, from blood, from things ſtrangled, and from fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From theſe words the Author draweth one <hi>Generall,</hi> and 3. <hi>particular</hi> Arguments. The <hi>Generall</hi> Argument runneth thus:</p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:166177:7"/>
                  <p> Whatſoever Law or Command of God is renewed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confirmed, re-eſtabliſhed under the Goſpel, after the abrogation of all Ceremoniall obſervations, generally, abſolutely, without any reſtriction, or limitation of <hi>Time, Place,</hi> or <hi>Perſons,</hi> that Law muſt needs be perpetual, till it be expreſly repealed and abrogated by the ſame Law giver. Now this Law againſt eating of Blood was ſo renewed. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Both Propoſitions are true; the former being grounded in <hi>Reaſon,</hi> the ſecond in <hi>Scripture;</hi> and conſequently the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion undeniable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> This Law was renewed by the Apoſtles with reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and limitation, and was to laſt no longer, but till Blood might be eaten with a Conſcience ſatisfied in its Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and without offence to weak brethren. And therefore cannot be perpetuall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R.</hi> We anſwer 1. This limitation is but a humane gloſſe, and we do not find the leaſt ground or hint of it in the whole word of God. We did ſhew, that God hath forbidden it in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall terms, without any limitation: Let them ſhew out of the word, that it was forbidden only for a time. It is a great preſumption in man, to limit the time of keeping Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, when God himſelf doth not limit it. In ſuch things we muſt deal conſiderably, and not follow the meer ungrounded conceits of Men, but the Rule, <hi>To the Law, and to the Testimony, if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is, becauſe there is no light in them, Iſa.</hi> 8.20.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Suppoſe it were ſo, then let us know, when it was, that Chriſtians came to know their libertie in this particular, and that this Law was aboliſhed. We do finde it obſerved, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.14, 20. which was about <hi>fourtie</hi> yeers after this Decree was made; And the pureſt Fathers in the primitive Church do report, that it was obſerved many <hi>hundred</hi> yeers after Chriſts Aſcention; as we may ſee in <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 1 <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> in his <hi>Apologet. cap.</hi> 8. where amongſt other things he ſaith, <hi>Inter temptamenta Chriſtianorum botulos cruore diſtentos ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monent, &amp;c.</hi> they did trie men, whether they were Chriſtians, by offering them puddings filled with blood, &amp;c. <hi>Origines, li.</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:166177:8"/>8. <hi>contra Celſum: Minutius Felix in Octavio</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Cyrillus Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolomit.</hi> in 17. <hi>catech. Chryſoſtome</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 15. Homil. 33. <hi>Baronius</hi> ſaith, it was yet in force in St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> times. Nay longer, in the times of <hi>Beda,</hi> and <hi>Rabanus Maurus, a. c.</hi> 855. as <hi>Trithemius</hi> reporteth: And we finde, that when the <hi>Pomeranians</hi> were convened to Chriſtianitie, <hi>a. c.</hi> 1120. this Law was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to them amongſt others, to abſtain from Blood, as <hi>Alph: Ciaconius in vitis pontif.</hi> witneſſes. <hi>Petrus Martyr</hi> in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.31. ſaith, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t verum fatear, neſcimus, quo tempore haec Lex deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit:</hi> To ſpeak the truth, we know not, when this Law did end. But in the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches it continued longer. <hi>Leo Imperator</hi> made a ſevere <hi>Conſtitution</hi> againſt eating of Blood, as impious, contrary to the Old and New Teſtament of Grace, invented onely for luxurie and the palates ſake; and therefore commanded not onely the delinquents to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely puniſhed, but even the Magiſtrates themſelves, in thoſe places, where the crime was committed, by reaſon of their careleſneſs, &amp;c. And the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches for the moſt part do obſerve this Law and Decree ſtill, as we may read of the <hi>Grecians</hi> in <hi>Breerewards</hi> inquiries, <hi>ch:</hi> 15. of the <hi>Aethiopians</hi> in <hi>Damicanus à Goes hiſtorie:</hi> of <hi>Moſcovites</hi> in <hi>Baron of Herverſtines</hi> Voyage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The very Turks abſtain from Blood, though a bloody Nation. All this is to ſhew, that not all men or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians know yet this part of their pretended Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and that conſequently by their own Judgment, the Law muſt ſtill be in force. We find in <hi>Beemans Theolog. Exercit:</hi> that there are yet many in <hi>Europe,</hi> in <hi>Germanie, Bohemiah, &amp;c.</hi> which abſtain from Blood, and that <hi>Sebaſtian Caſtellis,</hi> and <hi>Dan Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelocrater</hi> name ſome eminent men of them. But enough of this point.</p>
                  <p>The particular Arguments follow; which are drawn,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. From the <hi>Author</hi> of this Decree or Law the Holy Ghoſt, Apoſtles, and Elders; from whence he argueth thus:</p>
                  <p>Whatſoever Law is given by the Expreſſe Command and order of the Holy Ghoſt, and the Apoſtles, is binding of all Chriſtians, and perpetuall, till it be abrogated by the ſame Authority. But this Law was thus given. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:166177:8"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Obj:</hi> But this Law was to laſt only for a time, and was abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated afterwards, as may be prooved by divers places of Scripture, which ſhall be alledged by and by. <hi>Ergo</hi> it is not perpetuall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R.</hi> 1. This, is <hi>crambe his eocta</hi> &amp; a repetition of a former objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a meer humane gloſſe, and therefore not to be regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. 2. For the places of Scripture concerning the abrogation of this Law, we ſhall conſider them in order, as they ſhall be propoſed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. From the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of this duty: <hi>to lay upon you no greater bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den then theſe Neceſſary things,</hi> from whence the Author thus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth.</p>
                  <p>Whatſoever duty the Holy Ghoſt, and Apoſtles ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and make neceſſary to be obſerved under the Goſpel, without any reſtriction or medification, that is neceſſary ſtill, till it be abrogated by the ſame Holy Ghoſt and Apoſtles. Now this Law is ſuch. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Queſtion only is, what kind of <hi>Neceſſity</hi> is underſtood here in the Decree. To argue hereupon we ſay, that there is a twofold <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> a <hi>naturall</hi> and abſolute one, when a thing cannot be otherwiſe: and a <hi>morall</hi> conditionall Neceſſity, when a thing ſhall or ought not to be otherwiſe. This Law againſt Blood is of a Moral Neceſſity, <hi>neceſſitate praecepti,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the expreſſe will, and pleaſure of God, who hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to abſtain from Blood. Now it is neceſſary ſtill, as long as this Command is unrepealed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj:</hi> It was <hi>neceſſary</hi> only <hi>pro Tempore,</hi> to avoid the ſcandall of weak Brethren.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R.</hi> This is the great queſtion, whether fear of offence was ground and cauſe of renewing this Law: we cannot conceive it ſo. For 1. There were more things more offencive to the Jews, then eating of Blood, and yet not commanded to be obſerved, as uncircumciſion eſpecially, and eating of Swines fleſh, and the like: therefore fear of offence cannot be the cauſe. 2. Becauſe the holy Ghoſt in his grounds doth not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this at all; but the Apoſtles give other reaſons, becauſe all Ceremoniall Laws were an <hi>intollerable yoke, v:</hi> 10. <hi>a trouble, v:</hi> 19. <hi>a ſubverting of their ſouls, v:</hi> 24. but the abſtaining from
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:166177:9"/>Blood, a <hi>neceſſary</hi> thing, <hi>v:</hi> 18. as neceſſary to abſtain <hi>from Blood, as from fornication, v:</hi> 29. a thing which <hi>ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt to command, &amp;c.</hi> We may not lay falſe grounds for the abiding or deſtroying of the date of a Precept. The great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a Precepts continuance is the pleaſure of the Great Lawgiver. Let men take heed, to father a falſe ground upon the Holy Ghoſt, which is not mentioned; or to deſire a true ground of the Holy Ghoſt, which is mentioned, <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</hi> Let them ſhew the contrary pleaſure of the Holy Ghoſt as clearly, and expreſly, and we will yeeld. 3. Suppoſe fear of ſcandal was a ground, yet not the main, much leſſe the only ground, for the chief ground is Gods pleaſure. 4. Neither do we deny, but that it was a great offence to belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Jews, to ſee men eat Blood, and ſo it is to us; as great an offence, as to ſee men continue fornication, or any ſin againſt a Morall Command, and in this reſpect we grant, fear of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and of believers, nay of God, to be a ground of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. From the <hi>equality</hi> of the particulars forbidden in the Decree; where the Author thus concludeth:</p>
                  <p>Whatſoever Command is made as Neceſſarie, as the Law againſt Fornication, that is moral and perpetual. But the Law againſt Blood is made as neceſſarie. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For though we ſhould not ſay that eating of Blood were as great a ſin, as Fornication, in every reſpect, yet we may ſay, that by vertue of this Decree we are as much bound to abſtain from Blood, as from Fornication, as long as they are thus connexed and joyned together in one Law, till the equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie be taken away by a countermand. Thus, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.4. different ſins are forbidden, adulterie, fornication, theft, jeſting, &amp;c. Now though jeſting be not ſo great a ſin as Adultery, yet we muſt abſtain from one as well as the other; becauſe he that hath ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery,</hi> hath alſo ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not jeſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj:</hi> The Law againſt Fornication hath footing in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Law: not ſo the other particulars.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R:</hi> Even all the reſt have a footing in the Moral Law. Nay eating of Blood not onely forbidden by a moral Law, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.4.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166177:9"/>but more ſeverely threatned, then ſimple fornication Compare <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.16. <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.18. with <hi>Levit.</hi> 17.10. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.23.25. and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the expreſſions. Howſoever, till we have a repeal of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, we account eating of Blood as unlawful as Fornication.</p>
                  <p>And thus much of the Arguments againſt eating of Blood.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Followeth</hi> the conſideration of ſuch Arguments, as are held forth to prove the lawfulneſs of eating Blood, of which there are divers, but of no great moment.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Argument.</hi> If there be no meat unclean in it ſelf, <hi>i. e.</hi> in his own Nature, or by Gods forbidding it to be uſed, then neither is meat made of blood unclean, but to him that eſteemeth it ſo. But there is no meat unclean in it ſelf. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.14. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R:</hi> 1. We muſt diſtinguiſh the <hi>Major,</hi> and conſider what meat is, and whether Blood can properly be ſaid to be meat.</p>
                  <p>Three things muſt concur to make a thing to be meat. 1. Fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a thing for nouriſhment. 2. Gods allowance, or approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it for food. 3. The uſe of it by the cuſtome of men. Now though Blood may perhaps be fit for food, (which many Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians queſtion, and make it very unwholſome, as <hi>Galenus lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de facult. alim. c.</hi> 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23 <hi>&amp; de victus attennant. rat. c.</hi> 8. <hi>Dioſeorides lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 25. <hi>Weekerus in ſyntax. utr. Medic. li.</hi> 1 <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>Sennertus Inſtit. Medic. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4.) yet it hath no allowance from God, neither <hi>before,</hi> nor <hi>under,</hi> nor <hi>after</hi> the Law, but rather an abſolute inhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and reſtraint in all theſe 3 Ages: Nor hath it been uſed by men lawfully, from <hi>Adams</hi> days till the days of the Apoſtles, and afterwards for the ſpace of many hundred yeers, as it was proved above. <hi>Ergo</hi> it cannot properly be called meat. 2. We do not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from Blood, as unclean, ſeeing God never calleth it unclean; and almoſt all things were purged and cleanſed under the Law with blood, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22. and God would have it offered in ſacrifices to himſelf; and it did repreſent the holy Blood of Chriſt; all which particulars ſhew, that Blood is not unclean, neither for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born for that regard: but only becauſe it pleaſed the holy Ghoſt to forbid it to us. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.28. as being created for another end, to be the life of fleſh. <hi>Gen.</hi> 9 4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Arg:</hi> If there be no ſin committed by any uncleanneſs, that goeth into the mouth, then there can be no ſuch uncleanneſs in Blood, but ſin is not ſo commited, <hi>Mar:</hi> 7.15. <hi>Nothing from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166177:10"/>a man, that entreth into him, can defile him. Ergò.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R.</hi> 1. We muſt conſider the ſcope of Chriſt in theſe words, which was not to take away the diſtinction of meats, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the Phariſees for their hypocriſie, that they held thoſe things, which otherwiſe lawfull, yet did defile a man, if they were eaten with unwaſhen hands; ſo that Chriſt ſpeaketh here not of the matter, or thing eaten, but of the manner of eating; elſe Chriſt had not anſwered to the point, nor refuted the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: And this appears out of Chriſts own concluſion, <hi>Mar:</hi> 7.20. 2. Suppoſe Chriſt did ſpeak of things eaten likewiſe, yet he did not underſtand abſolutely al kinds of food, that none did defile a man; but he ſpake of ſuch, as knew their ordinary, lawfull food, which then they were about to receive. For there were then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain creatures unclean by the Law, of which the Lord could not ſay, that they did not defile a man, becauſe the Ceremonial Law, and the diſtinction of clean and unclean, was then yet in full force, and not abrogated, till after Chriſts death. 3. Suppoſe Chriſt did ſpeak of all kinds of meat, that may be eaten, yet the ſence is, that no meat can defile a man, in it ſelf, in its own nature, but may defile him <hi>per accidens,</hi> if it be expreſly forbidden by God, as we know blood was then, and is ſtill. 4. And if Chriſt had ſpoken of al kind of meat, yet it cannot be applied to blood, which was not forbidden by that diſtinguiſhing Law, <hi>Lev.</hi> 11.4. but by a Moral Law, above 800. yeers, afore that diſtinguiſhing Law was given to <hi>Moſes.</hi> 5. And is it probable, that Chriſt hath given leave here to eat all ſorts of food, when he knew, that the Apoſtles ſhortly after would prohibite blood? Or would the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles have croſſed Chriſts diſpenſation, if he had here allowed Blood? Or had not <hi>Peter</hi> deſpiſed Chriſts licence, nay his power to give liberty to eat of blood and all things, when he confeſſeth, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.14. that <hi>he had never eaten of any unclean thing?</hi> 6. We an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer again, that we do not forbear Blood, as unclean, but as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for another uſe, and therefore forbidden to us in the Law and Goſpel.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Argument.</hi> The Law it ſelf alloweth ſome to eat blood. <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.21. therefore there was no morall uncleanneſs in it. Should the ſtranger be more priviledged, then the beleever?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R:</hi> 1. The Law never allowed any man to eat Blood. 2. We
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:166177:10"/>ſay ſtill, that there is no uncleanneſs in Blood. 3. The place, <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.21. ſheweth, God gave leave to aliens, to eat a carkaſe, not Blood, as was proved above in the 2d particular <hi>Argument</hi> out of <hi>Levit.</hi> 17.10. 4. If it was a priviledge to eat a carkaſe, then our Doggs have more priviledg then Men, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.31.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Argument,</hi> If Chriſt hath freed his people from Ordinances, <hi>Touch not, taſte not, handle not,</hi> then they ought not to make ſcruple in any ſuch caſes. But thus hath he done, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20, 21. <hi>Ergò.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R.</hi> 1. We muſt diſtinguiſh the <hi>Major,</hi> and conſider, what <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> are meant by the Apoſtles. And truly the <hi>Expoſitors</hi> are of different opinions concerning them. See <hi>Mayer</hi> upon the place: The ſoundeſt Fathers, and Divines take them, not for Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall or Moſaicall Ordinances, but for the traditions and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of thoſe Hereticks, and Philoſophers, which taught the worſhipping of Angels, and the abſtaining from certain Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures at certain times, as diſpleaſing to Angels. Thus <hi>Beza,</hi> and <hi>Zanchie</hi> underſtand it, and to them do I ſubſcribe, ſaith <hi>Mayer.</hi> See more in <hi>Bezas</hi> annotations upon the place: And in this ſence, the place will do them no good, <hi>Tertullian lib:</hi> 5. <hi>contra Marcion, negat haec ad legem Moſis pertinere.</hi> And learned <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> ſaith, that by <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Commandments,</hi> are underſtood ſuch things, as were commanded by humane Laws, and by <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Doctrines of Men</hi> are meant, <hi>quae â Philoſophis precipiebantur.</hi> But 2. ſuppoſed (not granted) that Ceremoniall Laws be here underſtood, then let them prove, that this Law againſt Blood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to <hi>Moſes</hi> Ceremoniall Laws only. The very ground of this miſtake is, that they will and do not diſtinguiſh, between the Laws given to <hi>Noah, ad quae addidit quaedam Chriſtus, dempſit nihil,</hi> ſaith <hi>Grotius;</hi> and the ceremonial Laws given to <hi>Moſes,</hi> which are aboliſhed, and that they refer the Law againſt Blood meerly to <hi>Moſes</hi> Laws, when it was given ſo many hundred yeers before.</p>
                  <p n="5">5: <hi>Argument:</hi> If we may eat, whatſoever God hath created to be eaten, and it be a Doctrine of Devils, to teach otherwiſe, then we may eat Blood, which is created to be eaten, and it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound Doctrine, to teach otherwiſe. But this is ſo. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.2, 3. <hi>Ergò.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R.</hi> 1. The ſcope of the Apoſtle is, to forewarn Chriſtians of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:166177:11"/>hereſies, which ſhould come in with Doctrines of Devils, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding to marry, and to eat fleſh, as <hi>proceeding à malo principio,</hi> as were the <hi>Encra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ites, Marcionites, Manichees, &amp;c.</hi> which is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon opinion of moſt Fathers, and Divines, amongſt them <hi>Auſtin, Calvin, Beza, Piſcator, Grotius,</hi> &amp;c. Thus the Text doth ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Blood, which was forbidden by God himſelf, not by thoſe Hereticks.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We do deny, that Blood was created to be eaten, but to be a means to contain and maintain life in Beaſts, as we did ſhew above, out of <hi>Gen:</hi> 9.7. <hi>Lev:</hi> 17.11. nay for this cauſe, the Lord did expreſly forbid the eating of it, in theſe two places alledged.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Apoſtle doth deſcribe the nature of thoſe Creatures, which were created to be eaten, that they muſt not only be good, and fit for food, but ſanctified by the word, and prayer, <hi>v:</hi> 5. to receive a Creature with thankſgiving, is not enough to make it lawfull to be eaten, unleſſe it be ſanctified, <hi>i: e:</hi> allowed to be eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, in the word, as <hi>Calvin</hi> expoundeth it. Now I pray, where is Blood ſanctified and allowed in the Word? I find a threefold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of it, <hi>before</hi> the Law, <hi>Gen:</hi> 9.4. <hi>under</hi> the Law, in many places, eſpecially <hi>Levit:</hi> 17.10 <hi>ſeq: after</hi> the Law, <hi>Act:</hi> 15.28, 29. but no allowance, no leave, no licenſe to eat it, in no place of Scripture. <hi>Ergò</hi> it is not ſanctified by the word, and conſequently not created to be eaten.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It is not probable, the Apoſtle would ſo quickly repeal the Apoſtles Decree, not above five years after the publiſhing of it. For ſo many years after, this Epiſtle was written: eſpecially, when about the ſame time, the Apoſtle did write to the Romans to be very circumſpect even in things lawfull, much more indifferent, and rather forbear the uſe of things lawfull, to avoid the offence of the weak, then to follow their own knowledg, with the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of others; <hi>Rom:</hi> 14.15.20.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Apoſtles themſelves being met together, in the preſence of <hi>Paul,</hi> did repeat, and reconfirm the Decree againſt Blood, the next year after this Epiſtle to <hi>Timothie</hi> was written, and reſolved again, that that Decree ſhould ſtill be obſerved by the Gentiles, <hi>Act.</hi> 21.25. Is it likely, that the Apoſtle ſhould of his own head, contrary to the Apoſtles mind and determination, give liberty to do here, which they had prohibited; and himſelf after this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:166177:11"/>was written, did prohibit and interdict again? We cannot conceive ſuch ficklenes in the Apoſtle.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Arg.</hi> If every Creature of God be good, and nothing to be refuſed, then Blood is good, and not to be refuſed. But every creature of God is good, &amp; nothing to be refuſed, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Ergò.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R.</hi> 1. This argument is but an old coat turned with a new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and a meer repetition of the former argument in other words. 2. It is true, <hi>Every Creature of God is good in it ſelf,</hi> and by Creation. So God ſaith himſelf, <hi>Gen:</hi> 1.31. but not always good, <hi>i: e:</hi> fit and lawfull to be eaten, and that in many reſpects, <hi>either</hi> becauſe it is unnaturall, <hi>or</hi> unwholſome, <hi>or</hi> forbidden by God, as Blood is. 3. Again it is true, <hi>Nothing to be refuſed, viz:</hi> whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is ſanctified and allowed by the word, <hi>v:</hi> 5. but he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, whatſoever is contrary to Nature, to the expreſſe word of God, and to our health, or inclination. Now we have proved fully, that the eating of Blood, if it be not againſt Nature and humanity, and many times prejudicious to our health, that yet it is directly contrary to the expreſſe word of God, in the Old and New Teſtament, and therefore may and ought to be refuſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> But this place ſpeaketh ſo generally, and largely of <hi>every</hi> Creature of God, that it may be received, if good for food, and not to be refuſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R.</hi> 1. The Apoſtle ſpeaketh <hi>either</hi> of every kind of fleſh, which thoſe above-named Hereticks did deny to be lawfully eaten: <hi>or</hi> of ſuch Creatures, as were created to be received and ſanctified, or allowed by the word for food, <hi>v:</hi> 5: which cannot be ſaid of Blood, as was ſhewn in the precedent argument: <hi>or</hi> of ſuch meat as was never, or ſhould not be forbidden by the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as Blood was forbidden: for elſe the Apoſtles had been guilty of inconſtancy, to forbid, and to allow; to forbid again, and allow again, over and over, the ſame things, to the ſame Perſons, which had been contrary to the Apoſtles profeſſion, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1.18. Howſoever, the Apoſtle doth not ſpeak of Blood, which was never uſed from the beginning of the world, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver acknowledged for ordinary food by Gods people, or fit to be eaten, but always forborn, always abhorred, becauſe alwayes forbidden.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is no good conſequence to ſay, whatſoever is a good
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:166177:12"/>Creature of God, and fit for food, may be eaten: The tree of knowledg of good and evil, was a good creature of God, &amp; good for food, pleaſant to the eyes, <hi>&amp;c. Gen:</hi> 3.6. and yet was not crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be eaten, or appointed for food, becauſe God forbad our firſt Parents at their very firſt entring into the Paradiſe, to eat of it. So blood though it may be good for food in it ſelf, yet was forbidden to Man, at the very beginning of a ſecond Creation of the world, and as ſoon as Blood might have been eaten, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Gods allowing him fleſh to eat. Therefore Blood is none of thoſe Creatures, which the Apoſtle counteth good for food, and created to be eaten.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We may retort theſe arguments againſt them upon a better ground; <hi>That</hi> Doctrine, which for the ſatisfying of carnall luſts, doth give liberty to eat thoſe Creatures, which the Holy Ghoſt under the Goſpel hath expreſly, and by name forbidden, by a publick, poſſitive Decree, without any repealing or limitation doth both wrong God and Man. But that Doctrine which do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> give liberty to eat Blood, doth give liberty to eat ſuch Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which the H: Ghoſt hath expreſly forbidden in the word under the Goſel: <hi>Ergo</hi> that Doctrine doth wrong God and Man. For that Men eat Blood is for wantonneſſe, and their palates ſake, eſpecially as it is dreſt in <hi>Italy, France,</hi> and here in great Houſes. Hence <hi>Leo Imper:</hi> in his 58. <hi>conſtitut:</hi> ſaith, <hi>Alii Lucri, alii gulae cauſâ, ſumm<hi rend="sup">â</hi> cum impudenti<hi rend="sup">â</hi> mandatum (DEI) contemnunt, in eſcomq: qu<hi rend="sup">â</hi> veſci vetitum est, ſanguinem convertunt.</hi> And afterwards ſpeaking of Puddings filled with Blood, he ſaith, it was <hi>impium ſoli gulae, inhiantium hominum inventum, &amp;c.</hi> Thus it appeareth that Blood is not of thoſe Creatures, which are good, <hi>ſcil:</hi> for food, and not to be refuſed.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Argument:</hi> If one part of the Decree may be put to an end, then we may without ſin ſo conclude of the reſt, that is not clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly morall. But one part is put to an end, the forbidding of eating Idols meat, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 10.27, 29. <hi>Ergò.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R:</hi> 1. The <hi>Major</hi> is not univerſally true, ſeeing that in one and the ſame Morall Commandement oft one part may be altered, and yet the reſt continue: as in the Doctrine of Sabbath, the day is changed, the duty remaineth.</p>
                  <p>But 2. The <hi>Minor</hi> is falſe in the particular alleadged, becauſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:166177:12"/>the Decree concerning Idols meat laſted as yet above <hi>five and thirtie</hi> yeers af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Epiſtle to <hi>Timothie</hi> was written, nay after the total deſtruction of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem by <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> when there was hardly a Jew ſeen, that might be offended: even to the latter days of St. <hi>John,</hi> when the book of <hi>Revelation</hi> was written, and the Goſpel of Chriſt diſperſed through the whole world For even then the holy Ghoſt found ſault with the Churches of <hi>Pergamus,</hi> and <hi>Thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atira,</hi> for eating things ſacrificed to Idols. <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.14.20. Therefore it cannot be proved, that the Apoſtle ſhould have abrogated that part of the Decree ſo many yeers before, in this Epiſtle.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And to anſwer to the Apoſtles words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.27. there were <hi>two</hi> ſorts of Idols meat; <hi>One</hi> ſort was that part of the ſacrifice which was not onely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to their falſe gods, but eaten alſo at the Idols feaſts, in the Idols Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: The other ſort was a portion of thoſe ſacrifices, which was left, and did belong to the Prieſt, and either ſold in ſhambles, or eaten in private houſes. The <hi>firſt</hi> ſort of Idols meat was abſolutely forbidden to Chriſtians, which durſt not ſo much, as be preſent at ſuch feaſts and ſacrifices. The <hi>other</hi> ſort of Idols meat Chriſtians might eat, if they were invited by Gentiles to their private houſes; or if they bought it in the ſhambles, and did eat it at home. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree doth moſt properly ſpeak of the <hi>firſt</hi> ſort; and the Apoſtle in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. of the <hi>ſecond</hi> ſort. The <hi>reaſon</hi> is, becauſe that Idols meat, that was bought in ſhambles, and brought home to their private houſes, was not ſold nor eaten, as a ſacrifice, but as ordinarie meat, and ſo returned to his former nature again, and became common food, as it was before the ſacrifice; or as any other meat, that was ſold in ſhambles publickly: not unlike (if it be lawfull to compare holy things with unholy) to the bread and wine in the Lords Supper, which is holy bread, and holy wine during the adminiſtration of the Sacrament, but what is left after it, returneth to his common Nature, and uſe, and may be eaten, or drunk, of children, Heathen, Turks, Jews, and all men without ſin.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. We might as well draw an argument by ſuch an argumentation, that the Decree was aboliſhed in regard of Fornication, as well as of Blood. For if we may argue from the aboliſhing of one part of the Decree, to the aboliſhing of two other parts of the ſame Decree; then we may with a better conſequence argue from the aboliſhing of the three firſt particulars of the Decree, Idols meat, Blood, and ſtrangled; to the aboliſhing of the fourth particular, which is Fornication. But we do denie, that the Decree was aboliſhed in regard of Fornication, and ſo neither in the reſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj:</hi> But Idols meat might alſo be eaten in the Idols Temple, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 8.9, 10. where we find the <hi>Beleever ſitting in the Idols Temple,</hi> and yet eating with a good conſcience, if he do not abuſe his liberty. <hi>Ergo</hi> the Decree was in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of both ſorts of Idols meat aboliſhed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R:</hi> 1. The Apoſtle ſpeaketh of <hi>ſitting in the Idols Temple,</hi> not by way of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, or permiſſion, but by way of reproof, as of a thing altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, ſo <hi>Beza</hi> ſaith upon the place: <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ponit exemplum accubitus in Idolorum templo: quod factum Corinthii malè inter res medias numerabant, cùm ſimpliciter ſit prohibitum, ob loci circumſtantiam, etiam ceſſante offendiculo, &amp;c.</hi> The ſame he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peateth in divers places, and amongſt the reſt, upon <hi>Rom:</hi> 14.6. The ſame, ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> and ſhews in his <hi>Comment</hi> upon 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. that it is no leſſe then Idolatry, to eat Idols meats in the Holy Temple: and that ſuch perſons have communion with Devils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And as I remember, if not all, ſurely moſt of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:166177:13"/>the Fathers, and Divines are of this opinion, that it is a ſin in it ſelf, to ſit and eat Idols meat in an Idols Temple. 2. And if the contrary were true, and the thing lawfull, then it would be much more lawfull to go into Popiſh Churches, and to hear a <hi>Maſſe,</hi> or to ſee their Idolatry, when the <hi>Corinthians</hi> might not only be preſent and ſee, but partake of their ſacrifices, which <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, could not be done without yeelding to ſome rites and ceremonies uſed in honour of Idols, and falſe Gods; a thing utterly unlawfull in it ſelf, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.24. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.25, 26. and in many places more. But our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines do abſolutely deny it to be lawfull to go to hear a <hi>Maſſe, &amp;c. Ergò</hi> much more to partake of Idols meat. And thus much concerning the Arguments that are brought in againſt, and for the eating of Blood. Our duty is, to prove all things, and to keep that, which is good.</p>
                  <p>For a <hi>concluſion,</hi> ſeeing there are <hi>three</hi> ſorts of opinions about this queſtion; The <hi>firſt</hi> accounting it abſolutely unlawfull; the <hi>ſecond</hi> abſolutely lawfull; the <hi>third</hi> doubting of it; Let us ſpeak a word to every one of them; to the <hi>Firſt</hi> a word of <hi>confirmation,</hi> to the <hi>Second</hi> a word of <hi>conviction;</hi> to the <hi>Third</hi> a word of <hi>caution;</hi> to ſhew them all, that by Gods Law they ought to abſtain from Blood.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>To ſuch,</hi> as account the eating of Blood abſolutely unlawfull:</p>
                  <p>Where we have the expreſſe, literall word of God for a duty, before, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and after the Law, without any clear and evident repealing or abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of it, there we may ſafely reſt upon, ſubmit unto, and frame our practice according to it, rather then where we have no word of God, but only uncertain probabilities, and conceits of men.</p>
                  <p>Now we have the expreſſe, literall word of God, before, under, and after the Law, againſt eating of Blood, without any known repealing or abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of it; when nothing can be ſatisfactorily alleadged out of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe word of God, for the lawfulneſſe of it; nay not ſo much, as any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, but only the opinion and conceit of Men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergò</hi> we may reſt ſafely upon, ſubmit unto, and frame our practice accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this Truth, that is unlawfull to eat Blood.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>To thoſe,</hi> that account eating of Blood abſolutely lawfull.</p>
                  <p>Where there is an evident ſcandall given to the Brethren, by the eating of any thing lawfull, indifferent, doubtfull, there we are bound to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain rather from the uſe of it, then to receive it with offence. <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.21.</p>
                  <p>Now there is an evident offence given to many brethren, by eating of Blood.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergò</hi> they are bound in conſcience to abſtain from it, to avoid offence.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>To ſuch,</hi> as doubt of it, whether it be lawfull or not:</p>
                  <p>Whaſoever is not done in faith, is ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. that is, whatſoever a man doth, being not fully perſwaded and convinced in his conſcience, upon good grounds, of the lawfulneſſe of it, that is ſin to him. Now whoſoever eateth Blood doubting, whether he may eat it or not, doth not eat it in faith. <hi>Ergò</hi> it is ſin in and to him.</p>
                  <p>It is no ſin in us if we abſtain from Blood: It may be a ſin to us, if we eat Blood. The ſafeſt way, the beſt way: He that maketh no conſcience in little things, will hardly do it in greater. The Lord give us grace to practice the Apoſtles rule, which he giveth, 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 5.22.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abſtain from all appearance of evill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
